Guide to the George Wesley Johnson Papers, 1829-1939 RL.10124
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George Wesley Johnson papers
1829-1939
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Johnson, George Wesley
RL.10124
10 Linear Feet 7 boxes, 2,620 items and 77 vols.
Correspondence, daybooks, in the early 1840s, ledgers, notebooks, accounts, bills, receipts, orders, promissory notes, postal records, and other papers (chiefly 1831-1888) of George Wesley Johnson and of his family. The material pertains to Tennessee agriculture, purchases of goods in Philadelphia and other northern cities before and after the Civil War, Wake Forest College, the University of North Carolina, Greensboro Female College, economic conditions after the Civil War, and the mercantile activities of the Johnsons.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical note
George W. Johnson was a postmaster in Farmington, North Carolina from 1838-1856. He also served the public as a justice of the peace, general merchant, and farmer. His brother and business partner was James M. Johnson. Another brother, Hiram, also had a financial interest in the mercantile establishment.
George W. Johnson's son, Francis Marion Johnson, was a student at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
Collection Overview
This collection contains business and family papers of George W. Johnson, postmaster, justice of the peace, general merchant, and farmer; of his brother and business partner, James M. Johnson; of George W. Johnson's son, Francis Marion Johnson; and of other members of the family.
The collection contains letters to George W. Johnson from friends in Tennessee relative to agricultural and economic conditions there, 1838-1844; letters between George W. and James M. Johnson while one or the other bought goods in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, before the Civil War; bills, accounts, receipts, orders, promissory notes, and letters of a business nature, including occasional reference to another brother of George W. Johnson, Hiram, who had a financial interest in the mercantile establishment; numerous letters from George W. Johnson, his wife, Martha Johnson, and friends, including one at Wake Forest College, North Carolina, to Francis Marion Johnson while the latter was a student at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, 1855-1858; letters, 1858-1861, from another brother of George W. Johnson, J. H. Johnson, who-was operating a store at East Bend in Yadkin County, North Carolina, as well as references to the debt of Olin High School, North Carolina, notices of meetings of Mocksville Lodge No. 134, letters to Martha Johnson from her daughter, Jennie, while a student at Greensboro Female College, North Carolina, 1857-1859, prices of foods and general commodities, letters from Eagle Mills, Buffalo Paper Mills, and W. Turner's cotton mill at Turnersburg, North Carolina, and bills of lading for various commodities.
Material during the Civil War period is limited to a few letters in 1863 from W. G. Johnson (younger brother of George W. Johnson) near Kinston, North Carolina; tax in kind returns and a petition from Francis Marion Johnson asking for military exemption on the basis of operating a grist mill. Postwar material consists largely of mercantile records of the Farmington store showing that goods were purchased from wholesale firms in New York City; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Richmond and Lynchburg, Virginia; Baltimore, Maryland; and Winston-Salem, Charlotte, Wilmington, and Salisbury, North Carolina.
Volumes consist of small notebooks, recording goods bought by George W. Johnson; daybooks; ledgers; postal records of the Farmington, North Carolina, post office, 1838-1856, including postage books, newspaper postage books, and receipt books for registered letters; blacksmith accounts; itinerary of a journey made by George W. Johnson, S. Taylor, and D. N. Reynolds through North Carolina and Tennessee in 1836; minutes of the Farmington Lodge No. 46 of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows; and the Davie County Division of the Sons of Temperance. Included also are a few business letters from Nathaniel Boyden and Son, and a letter to Francis M. Johnson from a friend in Norfolk, Virginia, describing a typhoid epidemic in 1855.
Provenance
The George Wesley Johnson Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in January 1947.
General stores -- Records; Newspapers -- Circulation; Farmington (N.C.) -- History; Postmasters -- North Carolina; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Commerce; Women -- Education -- Southern States; North Carolina -- Economic conditions; Postal service -- North Carolina -- Davie County; Universities and colleges -- North Carolina; Agriculture -- Tennessee; Merchants -- North Carolina -- Davie County; Johnson family; Wake Forest College; Johnson, George Wesley; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; Greensboro College (N.C.)
- George Wesley Johnson papers, 1829-1939
  - Correspondence, 1829-1859 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1861-1907 and undated (Box 2)
  - Financial records, 1831-1852 (Box 2)
  - Financial records, 1853-1864, 1867-1884 (Box 3)
  - Financial records, 1885-1939 and undated (Box 4)
  - Misc. materials (Box 4)
  - Post Office material, 1836-1853 and undated (Box 5)
  - Printed material, 1863-1879 (Box 6)
  - Post Office records, undated (Box 6)
  - Bethlehem Church volume (Box 6)
  - Newspaper postage books, 1837-1854 (Box 7)
  - Meeting minutes, Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Farmington (NC) Lodge No. 46, 1853-1859 (Volume F:1996)
  - Proceedings, Sons of Temperance of North America, Grand Division of North Carolina, Davie Division, No. 18, 1853-1862 (Volume F:1997)
  - Account book, 1859-1861 (Volume F:1948)
  - Account book, 1860-1868 (Volume F:1949)
  - Account book, 1864-1869 (Volume F:1950)
  - Blacksmith account book, 1847 (Volume F:1951)
  - Day book, 1838 (Volume L:1953)
  - Day book, 1839 (Volume L:1954)
  - Day book, 1840 (Volume L:1955)
  - Day book, 1841-1843 (Box 7)
  - Day book, 1845-1846 (Volume L:1957)
  - Day book, 1846 (Volume F:1958)
  - Day book, 1847 (Volume L:1959)
  - Day book, 1849 (Volume L:1960)
  - Day book, 1851 (Volume F:1961)
  - Day book, 1852-1853 (Volume F:1962)
  - Day book, 1854 (Volume F:1952)
  - Day book, 1856 (Volume F:1963)
  - Day book, 1857 (Volume F:1964)
  - Day book, 1859 (Volume F:1965)
  - Day book, 1860 (Volume F:1966)
  - Day book, 1861-1862 (Volume F:1967)
  - Day book, 1873 (Volume F:1968)
  - Day book, 1873 (Volume F:1969)
  - Day book, 1874 (Volume F:1970)
  - Day book, 1875-1876 (Volume F:1971)
  - Day book, 1876-1877 (Volume F:1972)
  - Day book, 1878 (Volume F:1973)
  - Day book, 1879-1881 (Volume F:1974)
  - Day book, 1880-1881 (Volume F:1975)
  - Journal, 1860-1884 (Volume F:1977)
  - Ledger, 1836 (Volume F:1978)
  - Ledger, 1839 (Volume F:1979)
  - Ledger, 1840 (Volume F:1980)
  - Ledger, 1841 (Volume F:1981)
  - Ledger, 1843-1844 (Volume F:1982)
  - Ledger, 1847 (Volume F:1983)
  - Ledger, 1848 (Volume F:1984)
  - Ledger, 1849-1850 (Volume F:1985)
  - Ledger, 1851 (Volume F:1986)
  - Ledger, 1852 (Volume F:1987)
  - Ledger, 1854-1856 (Volume F:1988)
  - Ledger, 1857-1858 (Volume F:1989)
  - Ledger, 1857-1859 (Volume L:1990)
  - Ledger, 1858 (Volume F:1991)
  - Ledger, 1870 (Volume F:1992)
  - Newspaper postage book, 1854-1863 (Volume L:1995)
  - Journal, Travels through North Carolina and Tennessee, 1836 (Volume S:1976)